looking at data visually has always been
so useful to us humans
I mean numbers a great don't get me
wrong but I've always understood more
when it's laid out in front of me in
some kind of visual format we've talked
about benchmarking before about how we
can use timers to see how long certain
blocks of code take if you miss that
video you can find it in the top right
corner but today we're gonna be looking
at something much better we're gonna
take that data and look at it visually
hey what's up guys my name is Jonah
welcome back to my C++ series yeah okay
you guys get the point so this videos
gonna be a little bit different than the
usual ones I just thought I would mix it
up a little bit let me know what you
think of this kind of format what we're
gonna be talking about today is gonna be
really simple any one of you could just
take this and slap it into your own code
and actually use it in a matter of
minutes and the benefit that you're
gonna get is huge I mean I'm like doing
this kind of stuff in any kind of
project that I'm working on the kind of
long term that I'm gonna keep coming
back to and when I care about the
performance you know I've got a system
like this running because being able to
see so visually obviously just so so so
important but before we get into that I
just want to thank Skillshare for
sponsoring this video
Skillshare is an online learning
community with thousands of classes
covering dozens of creative and
entrepreneurial skills with unlimited
access to all of these classes if you
sign up for a premium membership which
is less than $10 per month it's really
one of the best places on the internet
that you can go to to learn just such a
wide variety of stuff they just have so
many classes on there anything from
illustration graphic design how to make
better videos how to make better
websites animation how to shoot better
photos classes on music production and
even interior design I mean who wouldn't
benefit by just making their space
better if you haven't checked out
Skillshare yet I encourage you guys to
do so there's really no reason not to
because there is a link in the
description to a two-month free trial
that should give you more than enough
time to check it out see if you'd like
it and learn something new and of course
that link to two months of fries you're
sharing membership is in the description
below
let's talk about profiling okay so here
we have a blank super floss project this
is just like whole sandbox that I like
to play with you guys know me I like to
start off with a completely blank
project that way you get to see
everything from scratch so the first
thing I want to do is actually write
some functions for us to profile there's
nothing here to actually record the
performance of we want to come up with
something for us to actually test out so
I'm just gonna write two functions
they're not gonna be anything
particularly exciting they're just gonna
print stuff off into the console I'll
stick a square root in one of them just
for fun but there's this can be
absolutely anything if you have your own
program of course you're gonna already
have all these functions this is just
something that I'm creating just some
dummy data for us to actually deal with
so with these functions ready to go the
next step is to see how long they take
to execute I did a video recently about
benchmarking in C++ I'll have it linked
in the top right corner make sure that
you check it out we're basically gonna
steal the timer class from there and use
it here and as you can see what I've
done is I'm just printing the name of
the timer along with how long it took in
milliseconds so that we know how long
our timer took using our timer is pretty
straightforward it's a scope based timer
which basically just means that we need
to construct an object for it to start
timeing and then upon disruption or in
other words when the scope ends it will
automatically stop and print our results
to the console let's go ahead and run
this program and see what we get okay so
here we have the result function - took
nine hundred and eighty-seven
milliseconds and then we annoyingly have
to scroll all the way back here to find
function one which actually took more
time at 1012 milliseconds cool so we can
get results out of this timer it's
pretty nice but obviously they are still
just numbers and not only that but they
are just really hard to find and it's
just super annoying to go through your
console looking for these numbers and
then trying to make sense of how
everything worked out enter
visualisation will actually enter Google
Chrome how many of you guess that we
would be using Google Chrome to
visualize our profiles so chrome
actually comes with some profiling tools
of its own amongst other development
tools obviously for things like web apps
or web pages and there's this particular
one called chrome tracing and it's
really bare bones really really simple
it lets us visualize our profile in kind
of a stack trace for you like this you
just type in chrome colon four slash
four slash tracing into your URL bar and
then there you have it
chrome tracing and because it's just
part of chrome it's most likely already
installed on your computer and ready to
go so as you can see it looks pretty
bare-bones and that's one of the things
that I love about it the way that it
works is it simply loads in a JSON file
which has all of the data in it so our
next step is to take all of that timing
data that we're recording with our timer
and put it into a JSON file in the
format that chrome tracing expects and
that's what we're gonna do now so back
here in our code just above our timer
class I've got this other class called
instrumental and this is this is quite a
simple class really all it's doing is
just formatting a JSON file and writing
it out into a file so we begin with this
begin session function really all that
is doing is opening a file and then
writing a header which is just
essentially the beginning of the JSON
file that needs to be in a particular
format for Chrome tracing and then the
end session does a similar thing but it
just writes out a simple footer closes
the file does all that kind of stuff and
we also have this concept of sessions
which is really simple now right profile
is the meat of this entire class this is
what writes and individually timed
profile so every time we run our timer
this is what we want to output and
you'll notice that at the end of this
once it's output all the board's JSON
into the output stream it actually
flushes it the reason we want to do this
every time we write a profile is because
just in case our program crashes or we
terminate it or whatever we don't want
to lose all of our profiling data we
want to kind of stream this into the
file as we go along so that if anything
like happens and we we can't end
smoothly everything all that data is
just safe and ready for us to actually
use so I'm gonna go ahead and rename
this into instrumentation timer just so
that it's a little bit more clear about
what it's used for because we're gonna
add some code here in a minute that
actually makes it like specifically use
the instrumentum and by the way this
concept of instrumentation is is going
through our code and adding like these
profiling times that's why all of this
is to do with instrumentation so again
the right profile function is exactly
what we're looking for so I'm gonna grab
that it uses profile result as a struct
that just contains
data such as the name the start and the
end so I'm just gonna call that function
here with the name the start and the end
time point okay so the next thing that
I'm going to do is scroll down to our
main function and what we need to do is
begin and end our sessions so what
begins session actually does is it
creates a new file with a given file
name we're just relying on the default
parameter here which is results dot JSON
and then everything in between the begin
session and end session gets put into
that specific profiling file and this
enables us to split up our profiling
data into multiple files which as you
can imagine can be quite useful for
example in a game we might want a
profile specifically the kind of loading
screen or the startup section of our
code but then when we're actually
rendering and we're running kind of
frame-to-frame and we've actually got
the gameplay that's like a completely
different ballgame altogether maybe we
want to profile that separately and by
having this concept of sessions we can
we can do that as as much as we want
alright so after just cleaning up our
code and fixing some errors a little bit
we have our running program you can see
it doesn't output anything into the
console anymore because it should all be
going into our results JSON file so
let's take a look at that if we open the
containing folder go to our root
directory here we have results our JSON
file let's just drop that into visual
studio to take a look at the text
contents of this file so we have
function one for example which is that
name of the time we have the duration
and then we also have the actual
starting time point TS I'm assuming
stands for timestamp and then we just
have like an array of this and that is
essentially all of the data that we need
to give chrome tracing so now that we
have this JSON file let's go ahead and
drop it into chrome tracing and see what
we get okay so check this out we have
our profiling data visualized now we
have function one function two but you
can see that something's a little bit
wrong on the timeline here it says 1000
microseconds and that's what the wall
duration is down here as well one
millisecond obviously this did not take
one millisecond it took a thousand
milliseconds so we're off by a factor of
a thousand let's go back and see if we
can fix that should be pretty simple if
we just change our time point cast to
cast into micro seconds instead of
milliseconds and we should have our
timing start and end data in the right
format for chrome tracing let's rerun
our program here to get some new data
bit back into chrome tracing and now you
can see where 2,000 milliseconds we've
got the right kind of scale so this is
really cool because obviously we can see
all this stuff visually we have function
one first then we run function two we
can see how long it takes and of course
as we saw earlier we can actually look
at this in kind of like a stack trace
format so let's go ahead and add another
function I'll call it run benchmarks
this will just call function 1 and
function two but now since we have like
another function up in the stack we
should be able to visualize this as well
I'll just print something out to the
console like running benchmarks and then
we'll stick that instrumentation timer
into this function as well we'll have to
give it a name of course which is
getting a little bit annoying but we'll
address that in a minute let's go ahead
and run our code and see what we get you
can see it's printing running benchmarks
here at the top and if we get this new
results like JSON file pop it into
chrome tracing there you have it we have
run benchmarks which calls function 1
followed by function 2 we can seal this
visually and we can see the entire time
of both of the benchmarks by looking at
wall duration of run benchmarks so this
is where she's getting somewhere now I
like this this is getting visual it's
really nice but unfortunately this run
benchmarks having to just just copy and
paste and then image the name of each
function that we call it's getting a
little bit annoying what can we do to
fix this up additionally this kind of
timing code is not something that we
want to run all the time in our program
there should be an easy way to shut all
of this off because of course it does
add some considerable overhead so we're
gonna solve both of these problems by
writing some macros I'm gonna define a
macro here called profile scope which is
gonna take your name as a parameter this
is basically just going to wrap our
instrumentation time a call will just
concatenate the line number here just so
that we can have a unique name for our
variable in case we have a bunch of
these in a row but we don't need the
double hash here depending on which
compiler you use I'm just going to use
it to be safe we're just concatenated
timer along with the line number here
now we can replace our instrumentation
timer calls with this profile scope
macro and then finally I'm just gonna
add a define here called profiling which
will set to 1 if this is set to 1 then
profiling is enabled which means we will
actually have profile score brought our
instrumentation timer and do all that
stuff however if it's disabled you can
see that we can just
have it just be empty which means that
it would replace profile scope with just
no occurred at all which effectively
just strips out that timer from any kind
of build which has profiling set to zero
so this is great but obviously doesn't
fix our problem of what if I just
introduced a new function like this run
app function and then I want to profile
the scope oh no I have to go back here
and change my string to run app that
just makes it a little bit more
cumbersome and annoying can we do
something about this yes of course we
can I'm going to write a new macro
called profile function no parameters
for this one this is just gonna call
profile scope but for the name it's
gonna take in the name of the function
which we can do using this compiler
macro called function don't forget to
include this into the else statement of
your macro like I did and then you can
replace profile scope with profile
function all throughout your code and
this is just going to be completely
magical we can just run this and it will
actually take the name of the function
and set that as the name of the profile
so if we drop this back into chrome
tracing you can see that we have the
same result as before we have run run
benchmarks function one function two but
this was not a string that we actually
put in ourselves this was done by the
preprocessor which is really cool
however we kind of run into a problem
here what if we have parameters and by
that I mean specifically overloaded
functions what if both of these
functions are called print function they
have the same function name but dead
they have different safe inches so in
other words we've added an int value
here which just adds its value to I and
then I have print function with that
parameter being called which is one
function and then the other function
without a parameter being cold if I run
this now and take a look at it they're
both gonna be called print function
because all that preprocessor function
defined is doing is taking the actual
name of the function which is print
function and that's it but we actually
want more information we want the
savings check can we do that
there's another one called func cig
which is a function signature if we plug
that in to our profiles go back and take
a look at this then of course we'll get
the entire function signature which is
great now there is this calling
convention that's part of the signature
which we don't really care about but of
course if you really wanted to just buy
some string processing you could easily
just strip that out before you put it
into your
JSON file okay awesome this is looking
pretty good
now you can take this profile function
macro and just put it into like
literally every single function of your
program if you want to see what this
looks like and if we were to like add a
namespace such as like benchmark or
something into here since we're using
that func macro of course we'll get all
of that information as well which is
really cool and in case there are areas
in your code that you want to profile
that I'm not functions specifically you
can seek that profile scorpion to any
scope whatsoever you can make an empty
scope if you need to and you'll see
everything here so here we have that
benchmark namespace is showing up
awesome so the other cool thing that
chrome tracing supports is multiple
threads you can actually set a thread ID
over here we're just setting it to zero
in this example and then if you do that
you can actually visualize all of your
threads running concurrently which first
of all is useful outside of profiling to
just see what on earth is going on in
your program that's one of the things
that I love about this but then of
course it makes timing in general and
profiling a lot more powerful so let's
go ahead and stick a thread ID into our
structure here and then we'll also
output that thread ID into our JSON file
of course now we need to go to our stop
function in our timer and see what
thread the time was actually run on so
that we can set up this thread ID and of
course the C++ standard library makes it
very difficult to actually retrieve the
thread ID as an actual integer but since
thread ID implements a hash function we
can just use this little trick we'll
pass our thread ID into that struct of
course into right profile and then let's
just go down here and change our
benchmarks a little bit so they actually
use multiple threads so that we can see
this thread stuff in action I initially
tried to use sed bind here but that
ended up being way more trouble than
it's worth because of course it's an
overload of an identically named
function and so you have to cast into
anyway it just becomes a huge mess it's
a lot easier to just use lambdas so I
used that
I also added in these two joins at the
end of this function just so that we
don't actually exit this run benchmark
function until both of these threads
have completed their work all right
let's run our new multi-threaded
benchmark which in general is not a good
multi-threading test because of all the
flushing that is pinging that is
happening from the C out function but
that's not the point of course our point
is actually to see the crew
tracing results and if we drop that in
you can see we have three distinct
threads that run benchmark one and then
the two other threads that it kicks off
I'm just gonna go back into the code and
get rid of that B thread we really
needed just that we can see the call
stack from that initial run benchmarks
thread which is just our main thread if
we read on this program and then drop in
that file there you have it so we have
run benchmarks which actually calls the
print function with no parameter by
itself and then the integer one is spun
off on a different thread and you can
see how we can visualize that in chrome
tracing which is super cool finally I
just want to show you guys more of a
real-world example of how you can use
this so here I have a branch of the
hazel engine that I wanted to profile
I've split it up into three sessions
startup run time and shutdown let's
start by taking a look at the startup so
this is pretty cool because you can see
how long it takes your application to
basically start up and here most the
time is spent in loading and mesh so you
can see the import is ready in the file
and we have a few other things going on
here that you could of course drill down
and take more of a look at if for
example it was just taking a little bit
too long to load and you weren't sure so
this is really cool because you get to
see everything visually obviously the
runtime is probably the most interesting
one this is actually the application as
it renders frame to frame so if you
drill down you can actually see exactly
how long a frame took so in this case
about 1 and 1/2 milliseconds that is the
duration of an entire frame you can see
how it gets a bit broken down here into
all the different parts for example it's
really easy to see how long the layer
update took compared to everything else
so yeah that's pretty much it I think
this stuff is super useful I'll have a
link in the description below to some
kind of like gist or something like that
that'll contain the code that I used in
this video the guys to try it out
yourselves anyway I hope you guys
enjoyed this video if you did please hit
that like button I want to see you guys
actually use this put it into your code
give it a shot right now and just
visualize everything that you're doing
it's amazing because not only is it
gonna help you benchmark you've heard
and see what pastas slow a pasta sauce
but if you're building something quite
big this will let you kind of visually
look at the code as it runs because as I
mentioned like it's not just the timing
it's not just like the actual daughter
of ok this took 60 milliseconds this
took 3 milliseconds this turbo but it's
not just that that's interesting it's
the actual structure of your entire code
especially if you've got numerous
threats being able to see something like
that is is so so so useful so let me
know what you thought of this in the
comment section below
hopefully it was useful to you guys
don't forget to check out the free two
months of Skillshare premium link in the
description below and I'll see you guys
next time goodbye
[Music]